က်ြန္ေတာ္တို႕ရွာေတြ့ထားေသာေနာက္ဆံုး ဗိဒီယိုအခ်က္အလက္မ်ားရွိတယ္
ဂရိနုိင္ငံရဲ့ တစ္ဦးခ်င္း၀င္ေငြမွာ အေၾကြးမ်ားစြာရွိေသာေၾကာင့္ စီးပြားေရးက်ဆင္းမႈမ်ားနဲ႕ ၾကံဳေတြ့ေနရတယ္
စီးပြားေရးက်ဆင္းမႈမ်ားနဲ႕ ၾကံဳေတြ့ေနရတယ္
အဲ.ဒါကို အလုပ္လက္မဲ့လူဦးေရနႈန္းကို ၾကည့္ျခင္းျဖင့္ သိသာနိုင္တယ္
၂၀၁၀ ေအာက္တိုဘာ မွ ၂၀၁၂ မတ္လ ကာလအထိ အလုပ္လက္မဲ့ ႏႈန္း ျမင့္တက္ေနခဲ့ျပီး
၂၀ ရာခို္င္ႏႈန္း သိသိသာသာ ေလ်ာ့က်သြားျခင္းဟာ
ၾကီးမားတဲ့ ကိန္းဂဏန္း ျဖစ္ျပီး ဒီလို အလုပ္လက္မဲ့ ျပသာနာ က လူ ငယ္ေတြ ကို ဆိုးဆုိးရြားရြား ထိခိုက္ေစ ျပီး
ဂရိ ႏိုင္ငံ မွာ အေျခအေန ဘယ္ေလာက္ဆိုးရြား ေစလဲ ဆိုတာ ေလ်ာ့တြက္ ထားပံု ရတယ္
သင္ဟာ အသက္ ၂၀ပိုင္းမွာ ရိွတဲ့ လူေတြ ရဲ႕ အလုပ္လက္မဲ့ ႏွူန္း ကို ေလ့လာ ၾကည့္မယ္ဆိုလွ်င္
မထင္ထားေလာက္ေအာင္ အလုပ္လက္မဲ့ႏႈန္း ျမင့္တက္ေနတာ ကို ေတြ႕ ရမယ္
ဂရိ ထံတြင္ ေစ်းကြက္ စီးပြား ေရး အတိုး ႏႈန္း ျမွင့္တက္ လာတယ္
အဲ့ လုိ ျဖစ္ျခင္း ဟာ ၾကာရွည္ေသာ အတိုးႏႈန္း ျဖစ္လာခဲ့တယ္
ျဖစ္ႏိုင္တဲ့ အေျခအေန ကို ေျပာၾကည့္ ရေအာင္
ဒါက ဂရိ
ဂရိ ႏုိင္ငံ ရဲ႕ ျဖစ္ႏိုင္ေသာ ရလဒ္
ဥရာပဇုန္မွာေနထိုင္ခြင္႔ရဖို ႔တစ္ခုတည္းေသာနည္းလမ္းကေတာ႕
တစ္စံုတစ္ေယာက္ကသူတို႔အေၾကြးေတြကိုတာ၀န္ယူႏိုင္မယ့္အာမခံလက္မွတ္ေရေပးရန္လိုအပ္ပါတယ္
ေရြးခ်ယ္ခြင္႔နည္းလမ္းတစ္ခုကသူတို႔က္ိုဥေရာပရဲ ႔က်န္ေဒသမ်ားသို႔အာမခံေပးကာသြားခြင္႔ျပဳျခင္းျဖစ္သည္
ဒီေနရာမွာဥေရာပရဲ႔အားအၾကီးဆံုးႏိုင္ငံဂ်ာမနီကအေရးပါဆံုးေနရာကပါ၀င္ေနတယ္
အာမခံေပးျခင္းႏွင္႔ပတ္သတ္ပီးလူေတြကေျပာက်တာက
အာမခံလက္မွတ္ရလ်ွင္အာမခံေၾကးဖ်က္ေတာက္ျခင္းခံရမည္
ထို႔ေၾကာင္႔အာမခံလုပ္ငန္းတစ္ခုလံုးရဲ႔အက်ိုးအျမတ္တစ္ခုလံုးကဆိုးရြားတဲ႔စီးပြားေရးအေျခအေနကိုအေထာက္အကူျပဳတယ္
ဂရိတြင္အလြန္ဆိုးရြားလွတဲ႔စီးပြားေရးရိွေနလို ႔အဲဒါကအလြန္ေၾကာက္မက္ဖြယ္အေ၇ာတစ္ခုျဖစ္ႏိုင္တယ္
႔အဲဒါကအလြန္ေၾကာက္မက္ဖြယ္အေ၇ာတစ္ခုျဖစ္ႏိုင္တယ္
သင္ ဒီမွာ အလုပ္လက္မဲ့ႏႈန္း ျမွင့္တက္ေနတာ ေတြ႕ရမယ္
ယခုလက္ရိွအေျခအေန က ေန ျပီးေတာ့ ပို ျပီး ဆုိးရြားလာ မယ္ဆိုရင္ ဘာျဖစ္လာမလဲ
ရုတ္တရက္ အစိုးရ ၀င္ေငြ သံုးစြဲ မႈကို ေလ်ာ့ခ် ပစ္ မယ္ဆိုရင္
ဘယ္သူ သိမွာလဲ ဒီေလာက္ ပမာဏ မ်ားမ်ား
ဒီလို အလုပ္လက္မဲ့ႏႈန္း ျမွင့္တက္ ျခင္းက ေငြေၾကး ကူညီေပးျခင္း အခ်ိဳ႕ နဲ႔ ဆိုးရြားေသာ စီးပြားေရး အေျခအေန ေၾကာင့္ ျဖစ္ ပါတယ္
ဒါေၾကာင့္ ဂရိ လူမ်ိဴး ေတြက ဒီ စီးပြားေရး ဆိုုးရြားမႈကို ပိုျပီး သံသယ ျဖစ္လာၾကပါတယ္
ဒါ မျဖစ္ခဲ့ဖူး ဆိုလွ်င္ … ငါတို႔ ျပီးခဲ့ေသာ ဗီဒီယို မွာ ေျပာခဲ့ေသးတယ္
ဒါ မျဖစ္ခဲ့ဖူး ဆိုလွ်င္ ဂရိ ႏိုင္ငံ ရဲ႕ ရွင္သန္ေသာ နည္းလမ္းက
ဥေရာပ ႏိုင္ ငံ ရဲ႕ ခြဲ ထြက္မႈ တစ္ရပ္ပင္ ျဖစ္ပါဦးလိမ့္မည္
ဥေရာပ တုိက္ ကေန ထြက္ ၾကည့္ ၾကပါစုိ႕
The Eurozone is the subset of European union countries that use the Euro as their currency.
And we've already talked about this, it would not be a painless process.
They would leave the Eurozone, the new currency would be the new Greek drachma
and with this it would be probably hugely devalued relative to the Euro
so you would have savings wiped out,
maybe not fully wiped out, but savings devalued for Greek savers,
and they know that already, that's why, because this outcome is looking more and more likely,
there is essentially a run on banks in Greece right now.
People are going, withdrawing their Euros, so they can stuff them in their mattresses,
so they won't be converted in devalued drachmas.
But this is having the effect of really weak [..?..]
potentially breaking down the banking system.
So you could have bank failures.
And the whole strategy of leaving the Eurozone,
leaving the Euro and going to the drachma,
would be to inflate away your liabilities,
would be literally to inflate away your debt obligations and your entitlement obligations,
but that inflation, and this has definitively happened in the past with countries in this situation,
could very easily turn to hyper inflation.
And so whether you look at austerity in this reality, where you get bailed out,
or you look at this reality over here,
in either situation, in the medium term, the economy can really fall apart,
it's really not clear how, outside of maybe extra generous bailout,
how that can be avoided.
And so in that situation, the economy falls apart.
And when economy falls apart, in a big way,
and you have major unemployment, it is a scary thing,
it can lead to social unrest.
And I'm not talking about 8%, 9% or 10% of uneployment rate like we have in US,
we are talking about 20%, 30%, 40% unemployment rate, even higher
in the folks that are likely to be unrestful socially,
which is the young people, so this could lead to social unrest,
and even radicalization, when people start worrying about whether they get
food on the table and they don't have a job,
they might start supporting people who have more radical views.
So just that by itself, is very, very scary proposition.
The history of Europe tells us that even if relatively small countries in Europe
fall apart in this way, it could have repercussions in the rest of Europe.
This is how the World War I and World War II got started.
Just that reason alone is reason enough for people to think very seriously about bailing Greece out.
And it doesn't come without moral consequences,
the counter-argument is - if we bailed them out
doesn't this reward mismanagement and overspending?
And even a little bit of shady accounting on their national economic statistics.
So, there's a very good reason, if you are a German tax payer,
then you are very suspicious of these bailouts.
Why we are keep running the cheques to the Greeks
if they are not willing to take some pain?
Now the Greek side of it, they say "Look, we've already taken amount of pain,
we are already kind of on the brink, possibly across the brink,
if you force even more pain on us,
then we are going to be in really, our society
is at the risk of falling apart. So, we are in a desperate situation.
This is not a time to kind of force a moral point on us."
So that by itself is a reason why people are worried
but then there is even a bigger reason
that Greece might not be the only,
it's only the first, maybe the worst, of the situations
but if Greece falls apart, and especially if the Eurozone - or, I should say, the European Union or Europe - is not able to bail out Greece
that's an implicit signal to the rest of world
that Europe is not able to essentially bail out its countries.
So, you see on this chart right over here,
Greece is not alone, it is definitely the worst,
but right behind it, you have Portugal.
And its debt, you have long-term debt with interest rates
looks like around the 12 or 13% range.
Portugal has a 93% debt to GDP ratio and already has very high unemployment rate.
If Greece is allowed to leave Eurozone and does not get bailed out,
investors are going to start wondering
"Well, hey, maybe Portugal is not going to get bailed out".
This going to make people expect more interest from Portugal
in order to lend them money, and they need money
in order to continue operating in the way they are operating,
but every increase in a percentage point, right over here,
is going to really eat into Portuguese GDP and kind of force them down its debt spiral.
Their debt as percentage of their GDP is almost 100%
if they have to pay an extra one percent on that,
that 1% is going to eat into their GDP
and it is going to force Portugal, the economy to slow down even more
and make it even more and more onerous
and they would just kind of go in the same direction as Greece.
And once again, Portugal is not alone, Italy has a very high debt to GDP,
Ireland - very high debt to GDP ratio,
Spain has a very high unemployment rate.
So, the fear here - and I guess there are two major fears -
one is that Greece by itself can become a point of instability in Europe,
but the second fear, if this thing isn't solved,
that this could cause a kind of contagion or a chain reaction through Europe,
that people start getting freaked out, they start wanting to not lend to these countries,
that becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy,
they might also have to leave the Eurozone.